<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Commons Codec</title>
  <author email="tobrien@apache.org">Tim O'Brien</author>
 </properties>

 <body>

  <section name="Commons Codec">

   <p>
    Welcome.  Commons Codec provides implementations of common
    encoders and decoders such as Base64, Hex, various phonetic
    encodings, and URLs.
   </p>

  </section>

  <section name="Impetus">
   <p>
     Codec was formed as an attempt to focus development effort on one
     definitive implementation of the Base64 encoder.  At the time of
     Codec's proposal, there were approximately 34 different Java
     classes that dealt with Base64 encoding spread over the
     Foundation's CVS repository.  Developers in the Jakarta Tomcat
     project had implemented an original version of the Base64 codec
     which had been copied by the Commons HttpClient and Apache XML
     project's XML-RPC subproject.  After almost one year, the two
     forked versions of Base64 had significantly diverged from one
     another.  XML-RPC had applied numerous fixes and patches which
     were not applied to the Commons HttpClient Base64.  Different 
     subprojects had differing implementations at various levels
     of compliance with the RFC 2045.
   </p>
   <p>
     Out of that confusing duplication of effort sprang this simple
     attempt to encourage code reuse among various projects.  While
     this package contains a abstract framework for the creation of
     encoders and decoders, Codec itself is primarily focused on
     providing functional utilities for working with common encodings.
   </p>
  </section>

  <section name="Releases">
   <ul>
    <li>Version 1.1 (from mirror)
     <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/binindex.cgi">binary</a>
     <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/sourceindex.cgi">source</a> (latest)</li>
   </ul>
  </section>

  <section name="Components">

   <p>
 	Codec is currently comprised of a modest set of utilities and a
 	simple framework for encoding and decoding both textual and binary data.
   </p>

   <subsection name="Common Encoders">
   	<table>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <a href="apidocs/org/apache/commons/codec/binary/Base64.html">
       	org.apache.commons.codec.binary.Base64</a>
      </td>
      <td>
       Provides Base64 content-transfer-encoding as defined in 
       <a href="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2045.txt">RFC 2045</a>. This
       encoder can optionally create 76 character chunked output
       for strict adherence to RFC 2045.
      </td>
      <td>
       Production
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <a href="apidocs/org/apache/commons/codec/binary/Hex.html">
       	org.apache.commons.codec.binary.Hex</a>
      </td>
      <td>
       Converts an array of bytes into an array of characters representing the
       hexadecimal values of each byte in order
      </td>
      <td>
       Production
      </td>
     </tr>
    </table>
   </subsection>
   
   <subsection name="Language Encoders">
   	<p>
	 Codec contains a number of commonly used language and phonetic encoders
    </p>
    <table>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <a href="apidocs/org/apache/commons/codec/language/Soundex.html">
       	org.apache.commons.codec.language.Soundex</a>
      </td>
      <td>
       Implementation of the Soundex algorithm.
      </td>
      <td>
       Production
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <a href="apidocs/org/apache/commons/codec/language/Metaphone.html">
       	org.apache.commons.codec.language.Metaphone</a>
      </td>
      <td>
       Implementation of the Metaphone algorithm.
      </td>
      <td>
       Production
      </td>
     </tr>
    </table>
   </subsection>
   
  </section>

 </body>
</document>
